and good evening everybody
welcome to the Board of Selectmen for
October 29 2019 I'd like to call us to
order and move to the approval of the
minutes for September 27th 2019 we
actually have a couple sets October 9th
and October 15th we'll make a motion to
approve the minutes of September 27th
2019 second all those in favor aye
and I moved to approve the minutes of
October 9 2009 teen second all those in
favor I make a motion to approve the
minutes of October 15th 2019 okay all
those in favor okay public comment for
items that are needed not on the agenda
this evening seeing none we'll move to
the exciting part of the meeting a
little bit bittersweet recognition of
Marie Harris a longtime Personnel Board
member when I say long time she started
as a child so you know you've you've
seen Marie here before several boards of
Selectmen representing the interests of
the town in collective bargaining
agreements with our negotiating
collective collective bargaining
agreements with our our employees and
Murray brought a value of of the
employee experience in Hingham to that
role on the Personnel Board which is so
important and carries the responsibility
of the board selectmen in in the town in
those negotiations and I think over the
years developed rapport and respect both
on this side of the table as well as the
other side of the table and that's not
an easy task so we have so appreciated
your work again over these many years
and very sensitive and extremely
important negotiations on behalf of it
so from a grateful Board of Selectmen if
you'd permit me I'd like to read our
Proclamation on behalf of the Board of
Selectmen this certificate is presented
to Murray Harrison recognition of 20
years of valuable contributions to the
Hingham Personnel Board the Board of
Selectmen wishes to express our deepest
appreciation for your dedication and
representing the interests of the town
and employees with compassion and
fairness your wisdom thoughtfulness and
graceful approach to negotiations will
guide the Personnel Board for years to
come
thank you for your service to our
community Karen a Johnson married Power
Joe Fisher hanging board of selectmen
this 29th day of October 20 19
[Applause]
[Music]
you're back at the table right where you
belong when you start before you start
Mary I have I am going to add to the
agenda a bylaw provision that says that
members of the Personnel Board have to
serve notice on us before they move out
of town but I just was two years notice
okay but I just wanted to thank everyone
I am just so grateful to be here to have
been a member of the Personnel Board for
so many years I have a wonderful group
that I've been privileged to work with
David pace a chair some iron Marion
Russell Khan and Jack Manning it's been
a great group we've accomplished a lot
and also I'd like to remember Nelson
Ross who was a wonderful mentor to all
of us and he he brought so much to the
table and he would just so appreciate it
the fact that he was such a good mentor
so very generous and in kind of this
time and it also I'm delighted to see
David dazzle here today he's he was a
very important part of the personnel
boards role and he helped us in a lot of
negotiations and in helping us to get
prepared and also I'd like to thank the
selectmen for the great job that you do
the countless hours that you spend
preparing studying the issues preparing
from meetings and in the employees of
the town they do a great job and just to
keep the residents happy and and it's
been wonderful living in Hagerman in my
own stellar resume and I just want to
thank everybody it's been a great run
thank you
they served with you an amazing Mendes
work lose a big big part of it but
you'll always be part of our team thank
you right now on to the business section
of our meeting and we have a
presentation from real estate counsel
Susan Murphy on the transfer of land at
2:30 field streets real estate Council
slash this is in connection with the
Alliance project that is down on Beale
Street near the stop and shop abutting
their Cove park no Joe was on the zoning
board during that permitting marrying
Karen this came before you before a town
meeting because there was a warrant
article thinking 2018 in order to offer
the town to authorize the selectmen to
accept the deed so this is a parcel that
is at the back end so you have the
development on the on the front part and
that's where the Hingham mutual building
always was then there was a wooded area
with a path through at that the
employees and hang a mutual used to use
during their lunch hour what happened to
take walks through the park and then
there was a grass area known as the
meadow which most people walking through
barbaracle Park never realized wasn't
part of the park there was it had four
people are familiar with it it had those
painted colorful painted dead trees so
back there so that's art during the 40d
process it was raised and it was even
raised to the subsidizing agency that
this was a you know sensitive area and
that something should be done with it by
the developer in order to conserve
preserve it and so the both the Board of
Selectmen through the memorandum of
agreement and the Zoning Board through
the permitting process worked through a
lot of different variations on the best
way to protect that land and in the end
Alliance came forward and said how about
we give it to the town and so that was
their offer as opposed to just putting a
conservation restriction or other type
of way of preserving it they offered to
deed it to the town and make it
officially part of the park
and so that was memorialized in the
memorandum of agreement as well as the
40d permit the requirement is that prior
to receiving a certificate of occupancy
they need to convey it to the to the
town with clear title
we've spent a month or two kind of
clearing up miscellaneous things in the
title there was a mortgage on it there
was a restrictions that were related to
their project but shouldn't have
affected the parcel and they've done
everything that I asked them to do with
respect to the title clearing and so
here here we are they've signed the deed
the request is that the board vote
tonight to accept the deed and to
execute it and then it will go in escrow
with instructions that they will not
record it until they're ready to record
all those title clearing documents
but I believe representatives are here
and they can talk about timing if you
have any questions for them so we're we
we will execute that deed tonight and
yeah I have the original here and and
I'm sorry do also have a copy of the
escrow agreement or I am do so I'm going
to give it to them with just a cover
which states that I'm delivering it to
them as counsel to the town in escrow
and that it may not be recorded until
they are prepared to record all the
title clearing matters so it's just a
standard Oscar letter that is typical to
real estate transactions okay Joe
are there any environmental concerns
about this parcel that we should be
aware of we're not aware of any
environmental concerns the only issues
that came up were related to potential
his historic issues because it's in an
area of potential historic I mean that's
part of the reason why I'd also wanted
to be preserved so that it would never
be you know disturbed for development
and once this deed is signed and
transferred are there any additional
obligations on the town that are being
triggered by this particular act no
there isn't there is an easement that is
being retained for that pathway that
existed historically for and him as I
said was used by king of mutual it's
actually being improved with a walkway
that was a that Lonnie was involved with
in order to make sure it was done in a
way that would be you know protect the
environment there and also would keep
people from wandering into the wooded
conservation areas I just finally I just
want to thank you because you've done a
lot of work on this and the town really
benefits from it so thank you know you
know this when the Memorandum of
Understanding came to the sport a few
years ago we said we were gonna do this
then we went to town meeting and said
we're gonna do it and now we're doing it
so it's it's it's helpful we knew this
was coming the works been thorough and I
I did my thanks as well I'm no other
questions questions or comments from the
public at this time
yes sir could you come to the podium
state your name and address
good evening madam chair members of the
board my name is ALV says I'm a
development manager with Alliance
residential I live in South Boston
that's I like to talk as required by our
permit I'm representing Alliance like to
present a check in the amount of
basically half a million dollars to fund
improvements at Plymouth River school
maintenance of bear Cove park and
assigned trailer for the police
department have the check here would
like to just ask usually where we're
sending money the other way thank you
Mary I don't know whether you want to
say anything about this because you yeah
so the board that worked thank you yeah
and first of all I I know Mary will
express our gratitude as well but we do
appreciate the support of the
development group with respect to these
municipal needs for the town yeah thank
you and and I'd be remiss if I didn't
acknowledge Paul Healy and Paul Deanna
and we're on the board at the time as
well and when in this agreement Alliance
agreed to pay the town a million dollars
for Plymouth River school and then
funding for the police department for
digital sign trailers and improvements
in bear Cove park and you know it's um
this is very helpful for the town we're
going to talk in a few minutes about all
the different capital needs in the town
and when we have partnerships and and
things of that nature it's very helpful
I'd also mention that I think there was
some funding for for Lynch field as well
and this was being paid out in a stage
of payments so this is this is part of
the entire payment and so I think that
the total the total consideration is
well over a million dollars and the town
is very very grateful for that okay so
the original oh you have to do the boat
so let's do that anybody else from the
audience care to make a comment raise a
question okay I would be I would just
add you know from my years on the zone
board working with this developer it's
been it's been a real contributions of
the town that they've made not just with
the check but within the entire process
and so the town thanks you this is the
project that put the town into the
uncontested 10% so it it was very
significant in many ways and again you
know I hearken back to Mary and Paul and
Paul Gannon because there was a lot of
hard work at that time and you know
working together with Alliance I think
has put the town in a position to then
control it's you know it's neighborhood
and ten Aleksey at us as well absolutely
remember that yet was you take a motion
yes I'll make a motion that the board
accept the deed of Rod B - 1b a portion
of parcel located at 230 Beale Street
from bear Cove investors LLC as
authorized pursuant to article 20 of the
2018 annual Town Meeting and delivers
such deed to the grantor subject to the
terms and conditions of the memorandum
of agreement dated October 27 2016 as
amended June 20th 2007
teen second any further discussion all
those in favor so if each of you would
sign and then Karen I'm gonna notarize
your signature this your free act indeed
yes it is thank you
think Mary was looking to make sure you
weren't eating away your they never know
what Tommy I was gonna Susan thank you
thank you AJ thank you thanks for being
here tonight appreciate it okay and
since we are at the cusp of our budget
season it's that time of year again when
we need to kind of set the stage and
talk a little bit about our finances our
long-term planning you know it's I think
it's it's so helpful to have a colleague
like Mary who is so knowledgeable about
the background and I think can summarize
it for all of us because it's an
important foundational place to
understand where where we're we're
jumping off from and I think that it is
in keeping with the long tradition of
the careful management and stewardship
of this community so without further ado
Mary and also I'm kind of a nerd when it
comes to numbers so I appreciate I
appreciate the board indulging me it's
so just as background and Bob I think
we've got the slides up on the wall
hopefully those will project well I'm
really here tonight because a couple of
weeks ago I got a call from Victor Belle
Terre the chair of the advisory
committee asking that a presentation
about capital that was that was put
together last year be shared again with
the advisory committee and and to the
extent possible try to make some updates
to it you know some of the things have
stayed the same but there is some new
information and just by way of context
for people you know we have a lot of
capital needs and that's resulting from
assets that are reaching the end of
their useful life or that they've
reached the end of their useful life
of changing demographics in town we also
have things like sea-level rise that
we're going to be talking about tonight
and for the past few years we've heard
about a lot of capital projects under
consideration from foster school to fire
stations to the building that were in
the harbour the South Shore Country Club
and we have a lot of master plan efforts
underway this year for the town for
recreation and affordable housing that
could generate additional needs so this
is just a little bit of a backdrop I'm
going to go through some background our
current situation the tax impact of new
debt and some conclusions and and you
know for Karen and Joe as as I look to
take this to the Advisory Committee on
November 12th I also view this as an
opportunity to incorporate any of your
thoughts and observations and be able to
convey to convey those to the Advisory
Committee on on November 12th just as
background this is this is census data
that was from the South hangin' study
group meeting but 50% of Hingham
households have an annual income of less
than $100,000 a year and if you look at
the charts on the right-hand side
according to census data by the year
2020 next year 47% of Hingham households
will have members age 65 and older and
you know like what we're seeing in the
South Shore is that many of our
communities are starting to age and and
Hingham is Hingham is very much in
keeping with that a statistic that's not
up here that has been pretty consistent
over time is the percentage of
households in Hingham that have children
enrolled in the Hingham public school
system has been about 25 percent for
many years and that really hasn't
changed so as as we hear about a lot of
about a lot of different things I think
it's important to keep in mind that that
we have a very large population it's
over 65 many on a fixed income and if
you look at that annual household income
it also says that many of our neighbors
and fellow citizens are probably feeling
economic pressure as as they look to
continue to stay here and hang them this
is hard to read but what I and I'm not
going to go through the details but you
know one of the things we talk about a
lot is our benchmark communities and and
where is hanging and relative to
benchmark communities and sometimes
sometimes we take a statistic against
our benchmark communities and we
sometimes kind of use it as as a bit of
a conclusion and I want to point out
just kind of four things relative to
hang them in our benchmark communities
first of all if you look at our attack
our total tax levy and that's the
information on the left-hand side of the
screen you'll see that there's a yellow
bar Hingham is about halfway down the
page our tax levy is about eighty four
million dollars that's how much we
collect from taxes and on the right hand
side what it shows is what percentage of
our tax base is from residential
property taxes and it's about eighty
nine percent so we need to remember that
as we're talking about taxes as we're
talking about potentially raising taxes
that eighty nine percent of that
increase we're all going to be paying
for you know we sometimes like to
compare ourselves to other communities
and you know I would point out that for
example if the community of needham if
you look on the right-hand side needham
gets about seventy seven percent of
their taxes from residential so they
have a more developed commercial base
this is also one of the reasons why our
board and and previous boards have been
looking at low-impact commercial
development particularly in the south
shore park because right now we have a
heavy reliance on residential property
taxes to pay for all the services and
capital projects that we like to enjoy
on the next page what you'll see is
again with benchmarking data there's all
kinds of things you can look at and one
of the things I looked at is where is
our average single-family property tax
bill and out of our benchmark
communities our single-family tax bill
ranks 11 out of 20 and when we think
about the benchmarking
in this twenty town comparison that
Marie Harris and the Personnel Board
have used for so long we kind of always
like to be around in the middle and
that's where and that's where we are
with our tax bill now the chart on the
right-hand side shows the average tax
rate and ours is eleven dollars and 81
cents per thousand dollars of assessed
value if you look just purely at our tax
rate we're ranked 17 out of 20 now if
you look only at that metric you could
conclude gee Hingham King emit Hingham
might be under taxing but I would say
that if you look at the average tax bill
and the fact that 89% of those taxes are
borne by residential property property
owners again we need to keep that in
mind as we look at funding some of these
large capital projects and just in terms
of our long term liabilities we are in a
very good place and this is one of the
reasons we're a triple-a bond rating
community from all three rating agencies
our pension is over two-thirds funded we
were one of the first communities in the
Commonwealth to fund a peb which is
other post-employment benefits that's
our obligation to pay retiree health
care benefits we're close to 20% funded
on that we are on track to have it
funded within 30 years and every year in
our operating budget we spend we
allocate about a million dollars to fund
that liability when I read about
communities and states and companies
that are unable to fulfill their
retirement commitments that they've made
to their employees I'm really proud of
him and I'm proud of what we're doing
here and you know Karen was on the board
when this started and it was during a
very tough time that the town said we're
going to get serious about open and here
we are ten years later and we're almost
20 percent of the way there our fund
balance which is our rainy day fund is
also very healthy this is a chart that
actually goes back from 1992 all the way
to 2018 and what you'll notice is in the
late
19 but before the year 2000 our fund
balance was on average about 22 or 23
percent and then in the early 2000s our
fund balance started to erode and steps
were taken by the town we did those
together and our fund balance has
significantly improved the dashed line
that you see on the chart that begins in
2011 is sort of the new accounting way
of looking at fund balance which is to
look at what we call the unassigned fund
balance some aspects of our rainy day
fund are committed to things so the the
Accounting Standards Board essentially
says that money is really not available
so as we look at it we're now looking at
that dashed line and the gray bars that
you see on the screen represent the
target that's part of our town financial
policy so you can see that our fund
balance level is actually higher than
the guideline in our financial policy
and as of the end of last fiscal year we
were six million dollars in excess of
the upper limit as we start looking at
some of these large capital projects
this is an area that we may want to look
at in terms of whether we would like to
apply some of that excess fund balance
to offset some of the cost I would sort
of call that tax relief in the last year
I've heard a lot of comments from people
about opinions about the town and the
degree to which the town has invested in
assets and with Gene Montgomery's help
we were able to learn that from two
thousand to two thousand eighteen we
have invested a hundred and seventy
seven million dollars in town assets or
just under ten percent per year and the
the table on the left-hand side shows
what is taxpayer funded and what is
state funded about 25 percent of that
hundred seventy seven million dollars
came from the state either CPC matching
funds
or money from the MSBA for east school
and for the Hingham middle school and
then the pie chart essentially shows
where it falls again because of the
state program about just about 60% of
our investment over the last 18 years
has been on school projects we've also
invested in CPC we've invested in
municipal facilities and then we've also
the yellow part of the pie chart is
capital outlay and really you know about
half of that money is for the schools
about half is for municipal you know
setting aside the the slices of the pie
I would suggest that spending ten
million dollars on our assets every year
is is a good thing and I think we do
invest in our infrastructure here in
Hingham I think we also are at a place
where many assets are reaching the end
of their useful life at the same time so
it may be that as we look at the next
ten years we're spending more than ten
million dollars a year this is just a
list of some of the projects that we've
spent it on schools a renovation of the
library the DPW facility and Carlson
fields the high school fields we
purchase land on the harbor the
Affordable Housing Opportunity Fund for
a road building program so as you look
at that investment we've tried to really
focus on a lot of different aspects of
our town infrastructure so if we talk
about our debt for a minute Hingham has
a legal debt margin of 309 million
dollars and and I equate this to you get
a credit card in the mail and it says
congratulations as it did to my 18 year
old son a few weeks ago congratulations
here is your credit card and you have a
credit limit of like twenty thousand
dollars well you know I would say okay
just because you have the ability to
spend that much money doesn't mean you
necessarily
should but from a legal perspective the
town of Hingham could take on 309
million dollars worth of debt if we
wanted to we don't want to thomas
shaking his head right now we have 61
million dollars in outstanding debt and
we have a financial policy that tells us
how much debt we want to carry at any
point in time and that's represented by
the black line on that chart and in 2021
we actually are now below that blue that
black line which means that we are below
the threshold for our debt policy so
this is a policy that's administered by
the Advisory Committee and that says
that as we're looking to take on new
debt we have capacity within our
financial policy if you look at our
outstanding debt our outstanding debt we
have two two pieces of it the excluded
debt which is a 20-year temporary tax
increase and non excluded debt
most of our excluded debt is primarily
school projects and what you can see
from the bar chart on the right-hand
side is by the year 2029 are a lot of
our debt is retired and again this is
for projects like East Elementary School
Plymouth River and foster improvements
the middle school the high school
athletic fields we also have non
excluded debt which is debt that we pay
for in our operating budget that's a lot
of municipal projects and again if you
look at the red the red bars on the
right-hand side a great deal of that
expires by the year 2029 so this year in
our budget we have an operating budget
of about a hundred and eight million
dollars and right now in that hundred
and eight million dollar budget we have
debt service charges of five point four
million dollars so you know again this
is the
a place that hits the operating budget
and what you'll see is out of that 5.4
million dollars 74 percent of it is for
school and school projects 13 percent of
it is for fields and recreation fire is
about 7% public works six percent we
have debt service on land and then a few
other miscellaneous things again I think
this is evidence that we are investing
in our infrastructure and it would also
say to me that as we're looking at as
we're looking at new capital projects we
have to be mindful of what we still have
to pay for we still have these bills
that we have to pay for so the current
year property tax bill on the average
assessed value residential home and and
Rick now and our Assessor was kind
enough to provide some of this
information the average assessed value
residential home in Hingham is now eight
hundred and forty-one thousand dollars
and interestingly enough in about the 16
months since I did this presentation
that went up by almost $50,000 and so if
your home is is assessed at eight
hundred forty-one thousand dollars your
property tax bill in a year is about ten
thousand dollars and that's a
combination of the tax levy the excluded
debt and community preservation and I
think it's noteworthy to point out that
but that that average tax bill is
actually just north of the property tax
deduction limit that has taken effect
with the changes to you know to our
taxes so now you know we sometimes used
to say well gee if we take on new debt
and we raise people's taxes we're giving
them an extra tax deduction so it's not
hitting people's wallets as much as much
as we think if you look at the average
tax bill if your home is assessed at
eight hundred forty-one thousand dollars
or more you're not going to have the
that deduction and so now let's talk
about what happens if we add some new
excluded deaths so remember that when we
have excluded that that's outside of the
levy and that's a 20-year tax increase
and the reason that I'm talking about
excluded that is because if we look at
our operating budget I don't think we
have the capacity to absorb a really big
capital project without significant cuts
to services because again our operating
budget can only increase by
two-and-a-half percent a year so if we
were for every ten million dollars in
new excluded debt that adds a hundred
dollars to a tax bill for the average
assessed value home so if your home is
valued at six hundred thousand dollars
your taxes won't yield taxes will maybe
go up by eighty dollars if your house is
valued at more so here's a table that I
put together that's probably a little
easier to look at this in the first
column you'll see different amounts of
new excluded debts so let's just go down
let's go down to the middle forty
million dollars if the town were to add
forty million dollars in new excluded
debt for the average assessed value home
your property tax bill in year one would
go up by four hundred and twenty-eight
dollars and when we finance capital
projects we do what's called level
principal payment which means that the
first year payment is the highest and
the year twenty payment is the lowest so
if we look at the average tax bill over
twenty years for that forty million
dollars it's three hundred forty eight
dollars and over twenty years it's just
under seven thousand dollars now I would
point out that we know that every year
our taxes are going to go up by that two
and a half percent amount which is about
two hundred fifty dollars on the average
assessed value home so again let's just
hypothetically say next year the town is
going to
add forty million dollars in excluded
debt if I'm an average assessed value
property tax holder my tax bill is going
to go up by $250 for the normal stuff
plus four hundred twenty eight dollars
now you know go down and say well we've
got a lot of capital needs so what if we
said gosh let's let's let's try to do a
lot of things at once let's take out a
hundred million dollars in debt and do
all kinds of projects that's a thousand
dollar tax bill increase in one year
plus again that two hundred fifty so as
we're thinking about some of these
things again let's remember that let's
remember the demographics about
household income ages of households in
the community and the fact that 89% of
taxes are borne by residential property
tax holders so again if I think of
needham if needham raises their taxes to
build build a new building whatever it
is they're their commercial property tax
owners are going to shoulder 25% of that
bill we don't have that circumstance
here in Hingham and so being mindful of
the demographics in Hingham is I think
pretty important you know with interest
rates I won't go into this in detail but
our financial advisors are recommending
that when we're budgeting long term
capital projects we should apply a three
and a half percent interest rate we know
that interest rates are lower than that
right now every quarter of a point saves
again on the average assessed value home
about about sixteen dollars and year one
so certainly the fact that interest
rates are lower than three and a half
percent right now would be helpful but
I'd also suggest that
especially as we get into numbers that
are in excess of 50 million dollars that
the tax bill impact is significant
whether the interest rate is three and a
half percent or three percent what is
the what is the town doing you know I
think we've we've talked about this a
little bit and last year Karen
spearheaded a senior means-tested
property tax circuit breaker that would
provide tax relief to to a greater a
greater number of our seniors for this
year we need to identify a funding
source and figure out how to pay for
that but I know this this board has
talked about that being important to us
so that we can mitigate the impact of
some of these projects we've talked
about identifying town assets that could
help defray the cost the the the largest
one to me right now is the excess
unrestricted fund balance of six million
dollars but I'd also say that once that
money is committed you know I think I
think there are a lot of different
groups with a lot of different projects
kind of eyeing that money so we have to
be thoughtful about about where it's
spent because we can spend it quicker
than we can save it pursuing grant and
funding opportunities exploring public
and private partnerships where it makes
sense and then lastly and you know Joe's
picked up as as the liaison on this but
evaluating appropriate commercial
development this is the work of the
South Hanham study group you know to the
extent that in Hingham as I like to say
we like we like really good services we
like nice buildings and we like low
taxes and so kind of pick any two
diversifying our tax base is a helpful
way to spread out the tax burden but
obviously and as we always do in Hingham
we want to do that with thought and with
care and understanding that there are a
lot of different implications
I just show you the the implication of
using excess fund balance and again I
took fifty million dollars because
construction costs are seem to be going
up so let's just say hypothetically we
took fifty million dollars in new
excluded debt and we said we're going to
take five of the six million dollars in
excess fund balance and apply it to tax
relief and and let's say we do that over
five years so so that we're spending a
million dollars in the first five years
of this project that would actually
reduce the tax impact on the average
assessed value home by twenty four
percent so what I would tell you is
that's significant and if you think
about the way we finance projects with
the debt service being the highest in
the first few years this is essentially
very much like what we did with the
meals tax revenue when we built the
middle school we essentially said we're
going to take six hundred thousand
dollars of meals tax revenue and use
that to pay the bills so that the
taxpayer isn't paying that bill we could
do something similar with the excess
fund balance and you know I would
suggest that it could be it could be
significant as we think about grants and
I think you know I think it's also worth
mentioning the MSBA which is you know
that the town for three years has has
applied to be part of the Massachusetts
School Building Authority program for
schools this is bringing some of our
state tax dollars into Hingham to help
defray the costs of schools and you know
I've I've I've heard a lot of things
like well you know we've the town's been
very fortunate to get money from the
state for East School in the middle
school absolutely I think we've gotten
thirty eight million dollars from the
state for those two schools and that's
terrific but I just want to show you
what what the MSBA program is worth and
again we don't we don't know what the
solution is with foster school we don't
know how much it would cost but let's
say hi
ethically the project cost is thirty
million dollars if we work with the MSBA
their minimum reimbursement is thirty
five percent so that would defray the
cost by ten and a half million dollars
and again the average taxpayer savings
on that that's that's one hundred twelve
dollars that a taxpayer doesn't have to
pay in year one for twenty years if a if
a foster school solution is 50 million
dollars the MS be a reimbursement
equates to about seventeen and a half
million dollars or one hundred and
eighty seven dollars for that you know
for the average assessed taxpayer so you
know this this is why we have been
diligent and we appreciate the school
committee being a partner on this in
applying for the MSP a program for now
the third year in a row and we should
hear what our status is you know as I
look at some of this I also I see the
potential benefit of the MSBA because it
says to me if we're bringing some of our
state dollars in here it probably means
that we can take on additional projects
that maybe we would have to space out a
little bit more than than we ordinarily
would because you know that first slide
I showed with all of the different
projects that we have you know several
years ago people started putting some
dollars to those and I don't think those
estimates are valid anymore so I didn't
want to do that but if you look at all
those projects and you add them up you
can get you can get to a hundred million
dollars very easily so this is where
being thoughtful about how quickly we
move and taking advantage of funding
opportunities becomes very important
couple conclusions you know every
Hingham taxpayer pays for capital
projects and while we have a lot of
different boards and committees that are
focused on a particular part of what
makes our communities so
I think it's important that we remember
all the time that our constituents are
the entire town because we're all sort
of in this together and secondly that's
not free money we pay for most projects
over a 20-year period and you know so as
soon as we bond a project it seems like
you know very very quickly we've got six
more projects that are queued up and
ready to go and we need to remember that
we still have 61 million dollars in debt
that we have to pay for the good news is
that we are below the limit of our debt
service levels defined in our town
financial policy so if the town were to
take on some additional debt the rating
agencies would see that as investment in
our infrastructure and you know they I
think they would receive that positively
similarly we have a lot of debt retiring
in 2028 and and remember that as we're
entering the FY 21 fiscal year we don't
necessarily bond a project until after
it's completed
so if Town Meeting were to approve a
capital project next year we may not
finance that for two or three years so
the good news is that as debt is
retiring our tax bills are going down
we're creating capacity in our budget I
would say and you know a major capital
project and to me I mean the number I'm
pulling out is anything over ten million
dollars is really hard to fit in the
operating budget I mean we know we have
operating budget pressure you know last
year we I mean we've we've bought a few
fire trucks we did some of the high
school field improvement project in the
past we we funded the renovation of the
central fire station within the
operating budget but as the cost of
these projects goes up and goes north of
ten million dollars it's just harder to
squeeze and it would be the equivalent
of saying take your basic household
budget
and now you know find $500 to pay every
month for the next 20 years hard to do
so I would I would say that if we're
going to do any of these major projects
it requires a dead exclusion and let's
be clear a dead exclusions a tax
increase and again one of the things
last year as I talked with the different
groups that were advancing projects as I
said to people in my opinion it's asking
asking somebody if they would like a new
building or a new something is one
question that's not the same question as
would you allow me to raise your taxes
by X dollars to pay for this new
building I think that we should we need
to be mindful that support for projects
doesn't necessarily translate to
acceptance or agreement for a tax
increase and that's where it becomes so
important to socialize these projects
and really consider the taxpayer impact
not just on individual projects but
cumulative and and that means that that
we may need to reduce the scope of some
projects we may need to defer some and
we need we may need to say no and this
board has said no a couple of times in
the last few years not always a popular
thing to do not always what we'd like
but we are mindful we are mindful of the
taxpayers and that 88% of these projects
are funded by tax payers excess fund
balance can provide some tax relief and
again I just say that the dollars only
go so far so we need to to choose how to
use them wisely I think the other piece
of this as we're looking at capital is
that this is a period of time where it's
really important for us to live within
our operating budget which means no
overrides again you know the average tax
bill goes up by a couple hundred dollars
every year we hear from people that
sometimes that's that's a difficult
budget challenge if we're going to be
looking at
debt exclusions for capital projects I
don't think it's advisable at the same
time to be asking people to open up
their wallet to fund more services as
well it's it's it's a little bit of a
challenge to other observations you know
continuing to fund those long term
liabilities the pension and the Oh
pepper really important so again in the
short term we could say gosh we're going
to take a few years off and we're going
to use that money to pay for some
buildings the rating agencies are going
to pay attention to that and and frankly
the investment returns we've seen
particularly in the last ten years have
been significant and I think we all
understand that those are obligations
that we have have made to current and
past employees and then you know lastly
and Karen I know this this was something
last year that that kind of caught your
attention it seems like we're kind of
entering this period now where you know
we have everyday capital outlay you need
a we need a new police car
we need IT for the schools we need you
know we need other stuff like that and
we have about a two million dollar
capital budget and every year or in the
past few years it seems like there have
been things that have come along that
cost maybe a couple hundred thousand
dollars where we say gosh we don't want
that to eat up a quarter of the capital
outlay budget because then we won't be
able to buy this everyday stuff that we
need and so they and so what's been
happening is we've been funding those
through a warrant article as opposed to
the capital outlay process so last year
the Town Hall roof the high school
windows and I think our board and again
this is a message I'm going to carry to
the Advisory Committee the vetting of
those warrant articles is not always as
rigorous and disciplined as the capital
outlay vetting process and and that's
such a good process in that committee
does such great work the other thing is
that that
capital is not counted as capital
spending according to the town financial
policy and so that really means that
we're spending more money on capital
than then we're than the target we've
set so my view is if we're gonna set a
target about capital spending let's
count it all and I know next year the
advice the Advisory Committee reviews
its financial policy every three years
and I think and gets up next year and
the other piece is that we've been
actually trying to accumulate non
excluded debt capacity by budgeting it
flat every year when we have these
projects were eating away at that and
that may be the right thing to do but it
sort of feels to me as if funding these
projects through a warrant article it's
it's feeling like a little bit of a
shortcut and I'm not I guess I would
just I think we're always so thoughtful
about different things that it seems to
me that we're kind of at a point where
that's either going to become a standard
practice or we're going to put some
guardrails around it and I guess what I
would advocate is it may be the right
thing to do but let's put some
guardrails around it let's put some kind
of a process around it so that we're
we're being as careful and thoughtful
about that spending as we can so I think
that's that's it questions well that's
that was incredible report informative
and I think reassuring to the town that
we have been prudent in exercising our
financial responsibilities and that
you've been quite thorough in your
review so so thank you I do have a
couple questions
the town just committed to purchase the
water company yep how does that play it
okay yes so that three hundred million
dollar debt limit yes it doesn't go
against it because there's Massachusetts
general law says that when you have an
enterprise like the water company that
has a revenue stream associated with it
it doesn't count so it's like a
different credit card off to the side
and and so it has no impact on this and
I know this was explaining the town
meeting but what's the impact on the
property tax bills zero right so the
water company will be again we will get
our water bills they may look a little
bit different but then they are Mary's
picture on the water bills that we pay
will fund the water company operations
and be funded through the enterprise
fund so no impact on so right so the
reason that it's not part of this
presentation is that it doesn't belong
part it to be part of correct um you'll
see in here you saw some little
footnotes but the the country-club is
not in here because it's a separate
entity the sewer is not in here because
it's a separate entity the water company
will be a separate entity you the report
talks about our debt I didn't see a
discussion about how often we refinance
it how was it interest rate set and how
long does the debt obligations that we
incur yeah so we typically fund
municipal debt for 20 years and the only
exceptions are like when we when we
purchased two fire trucks two years ago
we financed those over five years so Tom
and his capacity as the CFO along with
the Advisory Committee during the budget
process they look at all the interest
rates and periodically the town has
engaged an advisory committee
subcommittee to look at the debt and to
make recommendations to the to the chief
financial officer of the town about
whether it makes sense to finance the
majority of our long term debt is at two
Center lower and and we've actually fine
aunt
we've refinanced over the past six or
seven years at times to be opportunistic
and again our credit rating really helps
us on that because we are getting access
to the lowest rates and we also
refinance short-term notes we can roll
right short term debt and again that has
been a conversation with the Advisory
Committee and to your point we we've
gotten very favorable treatment not only
not only in terms of interest rates but
also access to capital yeah the
short-term rates we're getting debt for
you know 50 basis point eighty basis
points so less less than 1% so again
Jean Montgomery and her team do a
wonderful job at looking to say do we
stay in the short-term or do we move
into the long-term and that's an ongoing
regular part of the review process I
remember when I was on the advisory
committee about 6 or 7 years ago the
advisory committee actually made a
recommendation that while the short-term
rates were so good we said let's lock
some of this debt into long-term rates
so that we're not you know we we didn't
want the town to be sort of in the
arbitrage business but you know trying
to reduce that down shot exposure and
capital market advisories is a is an
important period of the town and you
know like we said again during the water
company discussions capital market
advisors has been here over the long
haul advising us on these kinds of
important considerations with respect to
the debt side of the of the balance
sheet and as we were going through the
discussions with the water company and
we had discussions with all of the
rating agencies we talked to them about
the about all these municipal projects
because we said look we're we're not
only looking at buying a water company
we're looking at doing these other
things and so the the rating agencies
through our financial advisors are aware
of the possibility of all these projects
the financial markets are prepared again
I think the real question is
the speed at which the taxpayers want us
to move that's that's the bigger one so
you think you've anticipated one of my
questions which was on page eight
we took talk about our debt of 5.4
million and I was going to ask you it
what what interest rate does that
reflect then it sounds like it's about
2% yeah and I really think your
presentation highlighted the need to
make sure that as we are looking at
growth in the town and I know the master
plan committee is looking at it that we
really focus on percent that we can do
something to help defer the residential
burden of taxes so you know cuz the
other piece of this that we look at is
that the the other place where our tax
base can grow is in new growth and you
know you know that's a combination of
somebody making improvements to their
home you know bumping out the back for
its new growth and our new growth
forecast for the next five years about
half a million dollars a year because
there isn't there isn't a lot of growth
you know the Alaia and the broad stone
bare Cove was a big element of new
growth they brought in about 400,000 and
new growth but there aren't a lot of
those projects so again the the
challenge of living within our means
over the next five years is is there's
gonna be a little bit more pressure
because we won't have the new growth
that we've enjoyed in the last couple of
years and a new growth aside from you
know home improvements I mean new growth
is a little give it give and get right
like we're getting tax dollars but we're
also having to provide additional
services so but you know to your point
the pies the pie for the moment and I
think we've got a we've got to be able
to share the pie
anything else well Mary began really
really well done presentation
you know I guess one thing I would point
out that I know we all know but I sort
of point out for the folks at home is
that you know the the financial policy
of the Advisory Committee that Mary
referenced has kind of a statement of
goals and one of the statements that
they make in their financial policies
the importance of financial diversity in
the town of Hingham so you know you
could escalate how you know home costs
you could escalate your tax base and you
would essentially drive away any
financial diversity within your your
demographic and I think it's really
important that we've stated as a goal
and it's a financial policy that all of
the boards stand behind that the that
our goal is to preserve is to preserve
that financial diversity within within
our population and so to Mary's point if
that is one of your goals then you do
have to come back to the slides not in
the early portions of Mary's
presentation that show you the effect on
an average household and and the income
of an average household in Hingham
you know I again I appreciate you are
highlighting the the amount by which our
unencumbered fund balance exceeds our
financial policy threshold and I also
appreciate you drawing attention to the
fact that we can really only spend that
once right so I think we need to be we
need to be collaborative and thoughtful
about how we deploy it so that we can
get the best bang for the buck with that
and you know I think throughout your
presentation you know use the term we
because when you live in an open Town
Meeting Town it is we it is us you know
so you know I think we're very fortunate
to have committed volunteers on elected
and appointed boards that will Shepherd
these kinds of questions and projects
through our town processes and
eventually present us with a responsible
asked and a responsible choice but you
know all along the way it's the
citizenry it's all of us our friends and
neighbors coming together around what
the priorities are and should be for
this town and and what those priorities
are and should be for this town within
you know within the financial forecast
and financial picture that that that
Mary's outlined so well so you know all
of the projects that Mary talked about
it like on page five you know we all
voted for those I see folks in the
audience tonight many of us worked on a
number of those projects together so we
are making choices for our community all
together and I think Mary's presentation
tonight helps give all of us the tools
that we need to I think analyze what
what the questions are and then the
impact of those questions should you
decide to proceed questions oh I guess I
just wanted to say that you know you're
absolutely right so on the last page
you know I guess I'd call it capital you
know I was concerned and it expresses
concern a number of times about capital
projects that have been self selected
out of the capital outlay process and to
Mary's point I think if you've ever
looked at the town's capital plan which
is included in your warrant book on an
annual basis you'll see that that every
department is planning out and you know
again to Mary's earlier point about we
don't invest in infrastructure well the
numbers show that we invest in
infrastructure and every department in
this town has a capital plan you know
we're not we're not ignoring the fact
that we we have we need assets to do our
jobs right and so you know I I was
concerned that that that folks could
pick cherry-pick things out of that list
and in essentially forge a different
path that didn't have the same I think
vetting process and the same financial
guardrails so I think Tom and Michelle
we're doing some looking at how
other communities address this similar
situation which is you know we have
tried on it on an annual basis to commit
a certain level of our operating dollars
to fund you know operating capital for
lack of a better term right and that's
capital that we're going to afford
within our letting and and so that you
know the question becomes outside that
particular capital allocation or there
are other things that we should that we
should pay for that we need to pay for
and and how should those projects travel
through the projects travel through the
process and so I think time and Michelle
we're gonna pull together some analysis
from other communities that might help
inform to your point you know what
should the parameters look like for
projects that might be too big you know
and might you know might take up too
much room within the operating capital
bucket but still should go through you
know some sort of processes I think to
be proposed as a warrant article to Town
Meeting so it's so important that that
happened and you hit the nail on the
head Karen it's it's identifying the the
policy that can both give the proper
direction but also allow the flexibility
needed on any given budgeting cycle so
it's it's that's exactly the research
that we're doing and I'd be I'm really
interested Mary after your discussions
with the icon to you know to get some
feedback on on that point I know I'm
Victor over the weekend was that the
Finance Committee's have an annual
meeting and he attended it last week and
he said tell me that he was in a
workshop and and one a you know a
neighboring community Arlington also I
think they're a triple triple but you
know really strong financial one of the
things that they do is they set a
capital threshold but it's everything so
they say we're going to spend five
percent of our budget on capital and
that includes the cash capital includes
the debt service and you know maybe five
percent isn't the right number maybe
that's not the right metric but they're
looking at all because right now I get
the idea that sometimes it's attractive
to make it a warrant article
you can say oh it's going to be funded
within the budget so we kind of have
this illusion that we're not paying for
it well we are paying for it and it it
just doesn't feel as rigorous and to me
we should prioritize things based on
need and if a warrant article is
submitted for something it doesn't go
through that prioritization process and
I know it doesn't feel right now right
and I I can't get my arms around exactly
how it should work but I think that it I
think there's danger or there's concern
I think that if we build this if we
build this sort of third lane for
capital expenditure without any
parameters you know I think you know I
think we were quickly over overstating
capital spending to your point to our
target and so and it's gonna put
pressure on the operating budget because
we're gonna have to pay for that debt
for 20 years so that's that's eating up
some capacity right I do think there is
this sort of notion that when it does
that it's sort of free because we don't
see it you don't see the kind of
financial room you know I love it's a
town that we've you know we've we've
done some things that I to me are really
important to preserve because I think
they really help our community you know
in some communities when you know when
there's revenue that comes in when their
state aid like some communities the
school department gets it so if your
school if your state aid gets cut the
school budgets got to figure out how to
pay for it you know some communities
they take all the benefits and the debt
and they allocate it out and say you
know this activity this is this is like
your whole budget and in Hingham we rise
and fall together with the revenue that
we get and on some of our shared costs
like the debt service and the health
insurance of some of those things we
rise and fall together I think that has
enhanced the co-operative nature of our
budgeting and our decision process and
so I hope we keep that yep because I
think it's
helps us I would agree any questions
from the audience on Mary's presentation
okay well thank you and good luck on
that tide I'd also say if either of you
have any additional thoughts to
incorporate for addcom I'm happy to you
know maybe get those two timer Michelle
and I'd like to reflect a everybody's
thoughts in this okay all right thank
you very much you were supposed to show
up in bathing suits well thank you I
believe that Sharon PI put some photos
in their packets I took those today so
they would be the freshness photos of
the status of the building many of you
know the history of this it's been a
long time coming
it originally was in visualised Town
Meeting almost three or four years ago
like 40-plus years it was original Astor
plan of 2007 to have this and we went to
a number of iterations of putting it out
for private development long story short
we ended up funding doing the
engineering and architectural study over
the first hundred and fifty thousand
from Town Meeting engineering to prime
was successful in getting us a seven
hundred thousand dollar grant from the
Seaport council so at the end of the day
the building itself is probably worth
about a million won so a large portion
of that is being paid for by the state a
lot of infrastructure costs because
essentially we have to bring water and
sewer all the way almost from Ironhorse
over to here so some of the costs on
this are where you look at the overall
budget which is a little over a million
six we have some unique situations of
the amount of infrastructure we had to
pull from quite a distance where
a flood zone the building had to be
built in elevation as we've been doing
with everything with the trustees at
Chris and myself all of our improvements
have been accounting for sea level rise
the first one as many of you know is the
baiting Beach restoration which many
people just thought was it's Beach grass
and whatever the significant part is the
Buried concrete wallets underneath that
that protects our parking lot and in
many ways even this building I also give
kudos to Susan Murphy who's been helping
us recently through this process and
town officials Mike Clancy's been very
helpful in working with our builder to
make sure everything's being done
according to Hoyle so long story short
we had some delays some of it based on
soil considerations but once we got
underway we originally built this design
this is a stick-built chapter 149
project and the filed sub bids alone
were about 450,000 and the bid was about
a million 150 we ended up getting a bid
by going modular closer to a million and
by doing modular the modular component
alone is about three hundred and eighty
two thousand was less than the file sub
bids alone so it was a savvy move by
engineering in us in the committee to
say let's go that route it had a little
time to the project but at the same time
as maven knew we've had a concessionaire
fire King Gregor Sarah who runs Tosca
and they've stuck with us for the last
you know two plus years while we've been
going through this I think it's gonna be
a good marriage between us because he's
made a quite a commitment to this
building and so the advantage in in
reality his little fire king bakery that
started and was now Tosca cafe is now
about a 250,000 square foot warehouse
distribution facility in Braintree which
he finished this year long story short
he told Tom and myself if we had this
building ready in the spring he wouldn't
have been ready he could not do a
250,000 square foot building and have
all of that operation being done and
paid the attention to his 2,000 square
foot kitchen here
someone's
some ways we look at this is a little
bit of a blessing in the sense that
we're going to get everything tight to
the weather and be ready to go in the
spring of next year he'll be ready he
can get all his kitchen work done he can
hire this person now we can work on how
we're going to manage the community room
which is going to be dovetailing with
you people because you know looking for
one day later licenses so this I think
in many ways the long story short is
we're getting a really solid building
the material is a superior semi strike a
loss he's done an excellent job in the
design of this it's really supposed to
look like a boat houses he reminds me
the white trim by the way will not be
white it's going to be painted that same
topi gray which they kind of called
Hingham gray so it'll be muted and even
the railing system alone in this
building is worth about $25,000 because
we're in an historic district and we're
using a PVC material but it's a milled
PVC the cap is mahogany the windows oh
like Marvin integrity windows with mo
Lian's inside and outside the the doors
are Andersen doors that are for this
type of climate the building was built
on helical piles about 75 helical clouds
the the the piles in the steel frame
which you see in the lower left-hand
corner
themselves worth about 125,000 dollars
now it's got a that's why the building
would be solid for a long period of time
but it it's not something that somebody
renting the community room is really
going to see you know but I think the
long start with with red cedar shingles
the design we have the roofs have a
30-year life span also by the way thank
you for doing the roof on the gazebo
which conveniently is matching the roof
shingles that we have so I think I've
just tried to give you some visuals of
the building the main one is the the
windows to the right there as you're
looking at the top picture are really
the take out windows for the vendor I'd
even get we get into the leads even the
door that's on the right hand side is a
Dutch door so if he's extremely busy
that can be a takeout window so we
really had a pretty good relationship
with him as we were designing
building the we also have benefited if
you look at the lower right-hand corner
of page one we have a new storm Swale
that is far superior to the the Swale we
had before in draining that parking that
needs to be a problem for years with the
farmers market if we had a heavy rain
that it wouldn't drain properly because
he had a swale that was largely silted
over this is a significant Swale still
goes in the same outfall but it is i
have heard very little from our coming
this summer which tells me this whales
working so and then if you look at the
walkway in the upper left-hand corner
that's an extension of the walkway many
of you seen that was done in conjunction
with the Harvard Development Committee
this past year it is going to be
extended along the area see that's
already stoned and as part of our
requirement as we take it all the way up
to 3a so that's really going to help a
lot as far as access you know we've got
the area through the Grove now along the
beach going out towards the boat ramp
parking lot and extending out to 3a
already you see a lot of people walking
this you'll go down there any given day
and it's it's much more of a destination
just for walking because we have a solid
path the decking in the upper right-hand
corner its IPE which is probably the
most expensive decking but it wears like
iron and really doesn't need to be
stained to maintain it'll weather to a
gray and that almost you know certainly
if I add in my lifetime we won't be
treating that deck the community room is
about a 550 square foot room pretty
close to the size of this room maybe
just a tad bit smaller I like seven
marks design we have a vaulted ceiling
right now it's all rough most of that
will be blue board and plaster except
the top area which will be acoustic tile
to control that the flooring in here is
going to be heavy duty commercial vinyl
plank kind of a beechwood gray type of
thing
you point out seat as well in the
picture that it is beadboard along the
side the picture in the middle on the
right where you see the triumph
contractors workbench there's actually a
mural that I think was in was that the
wooden house of pages or something I
think
in pages that has been preserved by the
Historical Society and they're willing
to donate that to us so that wall will
probably have that mural of the harbor
whenever it was supposed to be
representative of my forget bill 19th
century and the lower left-hand corner
is only showing you about two-thirds of
the vendors area which he builds ninety
percent of that out in order for us to
make this work it's almost like doing a
strip mall where you get a shell and he
has to build it all out he bemoans us
about that but it's how we had to make
the thing work in the area behind that
wall is a big walk-in cooler so he's got
storage on the second floor and the
restrooms alone are each about 500 but
350 square feet in order them to be
handicap accessible so a lot of the
dimensions of this building were
dictated by what we had to do by code
but again long story short we're going
to end up with a very solid durable
building and I think you know it's it's
been a cooperation of a lot of people
and I'll command ed who's actually
basically took over all the work on the
Life Guards this summer while I was
working on the building and we kind of
divi divi are things up among the
trustees so each of us has different
responsibilities and working with Tom's
office and Susan and Randy Sylvester's
been invaluable picking up the slack we
worked very well together we meet once a
week with the with the builders on
Wednesdays and Susan and Liz Welch and I
go over the budget on every every other
week so we're pretty comfortable where
we are right now price-wise the
advantage of module building is there's
not too many surprises the railing
system was an extra because they didn't
carry what historical wanted in order to
make the budget we were okay with that
but that was a delta of about 11,000 but
we had a $22,000 contingency I don't
envision anything of any consequence
coming on this that we haven't already
done the gas lines already been brought
in from Ship Street the wiring has
already been brought in it was a big
infrastructure projects in its own so
that's kind of it if there's any
questions
the board has sure
someone can I get my first hamburger
hopefully in May of next year yeah um
probably an expensive juice drink - it's
gonna be really really high-end snacks
and I think what impact does this have
on parking at the at the beach good
question is part of this project we
added 35 parking spaces as you pull into
the parking lot on the right hand side
the area that's gravel now is going to
be shelled we're going to put a shell in
there and the area that that will be
paved is the area closest to the
turnaround we across over the Swale so
we actually increase the overall parking
as you probably remember you're on the
zoning board I think we met choices with
the planning this was a leading question
I knew I knew the answer exactly we had
a fairly involved matrix of the
assumption that you had multiple things
going on at one time
that you had a perfect summer Saturday
with people wanted to be at the beach
and high tide was let's say at 11 a.m.
or noon the farmers market was still
going on and the snacks thing was
opening up and in fact we're even
limited as to when we can rent the
community room based on whether the
farmers market is his is closed so
there's gonna have to be a lot of
give-and-take on that but we understand
what that is but you know really all
things considered if you look at most
snack stands as it is I think we have
180 parking spaces and we've added about
another 30 most of them don't have this
many parking spaces I'm sure like
downtown Hingham some of the you know
sub shops and the restaurants wish they
have this much parking in front of them
so I think for a large portion of the
time we'll be fine it actually leads to
me to another point I think the other
thing we have to think of this building
what it allows us to do and the trustees
have been working with a hard
development on this is we can have more
activities down at the Harbor now
because to me this is largely a bathroom
project I've been blogging for years to
have bathrooms that are open other than
three hours on either side of high tide
nine nine weeks of the year so you look
at it it's we have a community room
would be great for small functions we'll
have a snack stand which I think gives
some vitality to that area but in the
vendor was responsible for maintaining
the restaurant facilities so the fact
that
you'll end up having those types of
restaurant facilities in an
infrastructure we can support other
things whether it's craft fairs or
communities like Burlington Vermont have
a maritime week
they have concerts at the gazebos we
have something can support that and then
the synergy with the vendor is you'll
want us to have things going on so if we
can fill those hundred and fifty parking
spaces on an on beach day those are
customers with somebody who we get a
percentage of his rent so when he hits a
certain threshold so that to me is a
real win-win almost on Mary's
public-private partnerships this should
be a strong one I think you know in the
trees that we're taking down and then
and we actually have to plant more right
because there's gonna be screening for
3a correctly yeah they'll be screening
of this still will be roll-on dumpsters
more like the ones that Square cafe uses
not a full size dumpster but the ones
you have to use down the square that you
know have to be you know emptied more
frequently but those will be screened
off and even the this chimney is
actually gonna hide you know the vent
for these so even that aesthetically is
better looking than your typical
building that's got some you know domed
aluminum you know vents stacked oh yeah
I have another leading question which is
how have the safety issues been
addressed because now we have a building
we're gonna have kids on the beach who
want to walk and get refreshments and
they're gonna be walking through a
parking lot unless we've got some
controls in place well hopefully they
will do the use the walkway that we've
run to the beach that was part of the
that's why I'm so as well so there's a
specific walkway intended for that
person intended just for that purpose
you know so it'll be a dedicated walkway
that goes right to the left-hand side of
the building and also is handicap
accessible that's the part of the the
deck system which is pretty significant
around this building that'll get a
wheelchair and everything coming that
way can will access that side of the
building so we can make great so I think
we've looked at most of the things that
happen I mean that doesn't mean some kid
isn't going to run across the parking
lot but we certainly going to define
that and now as you start to look at the
walkway extending on the beach in front
of the gazebo
I think people start using and we
you start looking at moving or swimming
lines you know cuz I don't think that
came out of this as tom knows it turns
out jurisdictionally we actually the
gazebo maybe is probably in trustees
land because if you extended ship Street
that was the border of where the deed
was when they did it the proper you
waited up for us to do the shingles I
think we're gonna need that synergy
anywhere i can situate they they run on
a third cliff they have a Maritime
Center and they rent a community room
and they have a real procedure and how
you get the one day look unless so I
think we're gonna be working a lot
together Mike how many years and how
this whole thing works you know I mean
thank you for this is we're all looking
forward to it
this is great no very um I think my
questions were we're all answered I'd
remind people as well that was about
$700,000 came from the Seaport bond
council so you know that this is this is
a project where a lot of different
stakeholders in it and I'm just so
appreciative of all of the many people
and you know Tom and Michele I know over
the summer that this is occupied a lot
of your time as well and I hope that
everybody who was involved in this as
they drive by take satisfaction and
saying hey I helped I helped build that
so you know and and grateful grateful
for eat well for you know being being
part of this you know might be like you
know next summer if you're starting in
May it might be nice to come in next
summer at some point with just like a
little bit of an update you know how's
it going what have we learned
how's the rental for the community room
what are we using it for sure right and
you know to the extent the one-day
liquor license program Sharon Perfetti
in our office really does a great job in
helping you sort of pull together the
kinds of materials that you need to make
that run
and if if if somebody's renting the
community room is the snack shack part
going to be open like how will that not
necessarily I mean you know he does not
have exclusivity on serving food there
he probably has a home-field advantage
that he has a kitchen there and no one
else does but so somebody can rent it
and in more cases than not you they're
outside caterers they're probably
bringing the food in almost like the
same thing you would do if you were
renting the old Derby or something like
yeah you know how that gets handled I
think it'd be similar to that but you
know so a private event would not
preclude the sort of regular activity of
the snack shack not in any way that I
think that's gonna be really important
going forward I think you know one that
we've pitched this as you know community
access for everybody so I think the
community room is a wonderful addition
to it but I wouldn't want it to affect
kind of the core the core activity yeah
and the design of the building that said
we came up with is such as your building
is pretty well set off in its own way
from takeout area so if somebody's
having a you know wedding pictures taken
you know it's under getting an ice cream
cone isn't necessarily right beside them
you know so I think that that should
work out well you know well and Alan
really appreciate the work of the
trustees as Mary said a lot of a lot of
people had a lot of hand in getting to
to to this point and you know I think
that I know that it was challenging to
meet the budgetary requirements here and
we appreciate your hard work
to that end but I I agree with you I
think that you know we're gonna hear
from Bill Reardon next I just think it
brings this whole new opportunity for
vitality down to the harbor and really
really appreciate your work on this
we're not hearing you can't get there
anymore
like we used to hear about the Whitney
Wharf bridge the bridge to nowhere
I think we hear less of that you know
and and also not when is it gonna go up
I'm hearing cue actually looks pretty
good you know so the comments from
people rolling down their window a
little more positive
well good for you for sticking with it
yeah thanks for coming in tonight
alright thanks thank you Harborwalk
dwarf walls resiliency project wow
that's a so I'm bill Reardon chairman of
the Harbor Development Committee Allen
had the lovely flashy pictures I did
want the selectmen to see what the
Boston Globe printed this is Long Wharf
today at 12:35 with the with the water
lapping and people walking through six
to eight inches of water today was the
highest tide for the fall it was one of
those king tides and the harbor
resiliency the wharf resiliency project
is focused right there
the only other flashy thing that I can
add happily is that and it speaks to
much of what Mary and discussed earlier
as you all know we are one-third to
one-half bridged and and very happily
through extensive work by Michele Tom
and particularly Ken Corson who I
absolutely wanted my hat is off to him
to have a low bid well below what we had
projected and a grant by the state of up
to 1/2 of the cost of dredging up to a
total of two million dollars means that
as Tom and I have discussed in
comparison to what we looked at at Town
Meeting a year ago where we said well it
may be four and a half million and we
may get something from the state or we
may not
and we'll bond the rest instead we are
looking at a situation where it's going
to be two point eight to three maybe
three to given more material but half of
that is going to be found by the state
and we have in the in the kitty if you
will
reserved for this purpose that amount so
I don't think there will be have to be
any borrowing so an example again of
trying to be opportunistic use the
chances you get and we just know great
thanks to this Commonwealth of
Massachusetts so my purpose tonight and
it is to give you a status report
because that's what it that's what it is
and I want to frame the issue a little
bit Tom I got a big version of this if
that's any better your call just to
orient those at home I think we're going
to be able to get up on the screen I'm
going to be talking about the the
resiliency and reconstruction of three
town owned Harbor wharves
the first is Town pier sometimes known
as Iron Horse Park although it's not
iron but and I'm told that it's actually
technically the victory Park or
something to something to that effect
the second parcel is the combination of
what is currently known as the Veterans
Memorial the Vietnam vet veterans
memorial as well as the mobile station
parcel that featured in Mary's slides
earlier where we purchased purchased
that is that picture up or okay you can
point that things out Thanks and the
third is very importantly Barnes Wharf
in which of course is subject to an
arrangement that the town has within a
maritime where they are running their
Maritime Center and they have building
plans to expand fairly dramatically the
the infrastructure and the assets that
they are having on on the wharf so on to
go back I think the last time that I met
with you was a joint meeting that Alan
and I had some time in the spring I
think it was in hiatus just before Town
Meeting
we were talking about just generally
conditions on the harbour we that was
obviously before the whole Water Company
issue it was before I believe the king
of maritime received their grant for the
float system so that wasn't in the
picture and as you know we've had some
personnel issues that have impacted how
the folks that we could work with on on
this project at the time that we met
with you I think we were thinking in
terms of it might be efficient to try to
move all three of these projects along a
matrix of permits to be to be granted at
home and maybe we could put up the
permit schedule now that we would try to
do those kind of simultaneously well as
as part of my understanding from Tom
last week that you really wanted to try
to get an update on this now and I we
had not had substantive meetings
recently in part because of our issues
in town I did reach out to bills and
Thomas our consultant longtime
consultant on this project and between
the last couple of days had an
opportunity to update with them where
where did the rate of the design stand
for each of the three different warps
where is what's the what's the permit
situation what's the timing and then
very importantly to pick up again on
Mary's point what are the alternatives
for for financing where might me look
outside of our own appropriation as a
town meeting so all of that got reviewed
today with our liaison Joe and Tom Mayo
later this afternoon I had a more
extensive discussion with feels and
Thomas and a couple of things you know
be became clear first is that there
there is a distinction now between kind
of where we stand with the different
projects Town pier is the furthest along
it's it's one of the more complicated
projects because it's going to involve
taking what is now parking on the
right-hand side as you go out to the
wharf and making that part of the park
because we're raising these you'll
remember we're raising the level of the
warps by about three and a half feet all
three of the warps that we're talking
about that creates a situation where you
could have water coming over and
gathering and pooling and it doesn't
have anywhere to go so from a design
perspective the folks at Beals and
Thomas had to deal with storm storm
water treatment and like Allen's swell
you can't simply just put it back into
the ocean you've got to do you know some
some treatment of that so all of those
things have worked in but Dylan Thomas
has gone very far with that and that is
that project is the farthest along from
it from a design standpoint almost ready
to come to the first group of permit
granters which are which are a member of
organizations within the town whether
it's the Conservation Commission or the
Planning Board or the CBA the other part
that enters into what what becomes their
recommendation bills in Thomas
recommendation to us and I need to copy
out everything I'm saying by
since this evening by saying that I'm
sharing material that I've I've only
gathered since the last time that my
committee met Bruce Mac aloni who's
co-chair of the committee is here
tonight he's hearing some of this for
the first time we have not had a chance
to meet you know vetted tested and you
know come forward with recommendation
but I'm just sharing in the interest of
status where are we so I learned a good
deal about and this municipal
vulnerability program and the financing
that is available from that there were
some schedules that were developed by
the engineering group last spring in
April that targeted going to the state
a couple of years not kind of all at
once in part because the permitting
might come through not all at once
because as I said Town pier is further
along barnesworth with some of its
complexities the back and forth with the
hang of maritime makes that one more
difficult Vietnam vet Veterans Park and
mobile is fairly straightforward so that
one's pretty far along as well but it
turns out that this program to request
grants of the state and this has been
very visible by the governor he said
look I'm gonna have more money for this
but the program is fairly new it's only
been within the last two to three years
they don't have a set schedule for
filing to make a grant request nor do
they have a set schedule for when they
are going to tell you how much money you
get but they do have one requirement and
that is that the year that you get it
you must spend it by the end of that
fiscal year this is very tough for towns
so for example the next available slot
to request would be sometime in
mid-november
two to three weeks from now for our
grant that would be made
perhaps in the December early January
time frame but it would have to be spent
by June 30th realistically we're just
not there for for this to participate in
that cycle so I had the conversation
with Eric gloss and who remember that
Beals and Thomas are the firm that did
help us to get our certification as a
municipal vulnerability a certified town
and we we have that in hand so they are
very familiar with this process so I
asked Eric I said well given the fact
that there is no set timeframe what do
you expect is reasonable here given that
the governor has made a point of saying
hey resiliency is an issue I've got a
we've got to push more money there and
his his expectation is that probably
sometime in the spring perhaps late
spring perhaps around
meeting there will be another
opportunity to request grants probably
in the early summer early to mid summer
and that would allow a municipality to
gear up plan and actually do a project
and get it completed before June 30 of
2021 so there's that aspect of kind of
tying the the funding into the the
permit process and the other part that
and erekt wanted to share with me is he
said you know these are complicated
programs and and the draft permit matrix
that Thomas put up shows the number of
different permits that are required from
so many different agencies whenever you
get near the water you you end up
touching a lot of requirements and
agencies so Eric's view is what they
believe they've been very thorough and
they're designed for example of town
pier but they would almost like to go
forward with a straw man to see if there
are things that arise that might impact
the later two filings for for veterans
and and for barns so again that seems to
point to a feeling that look what can we
realistically do I've always argued for
we need to be opportunistic and we
depress these things forward especially
given pictures like this and what we saw
in March of 2018 but I don't want to try
to do so much especially when we're
lacking somewhat and its internal
engineering resources to to make all of
all of this happen so Eric's
recommendation to us which we'll
consider in our committee and come back
to you and we have you know more more
meat on the bone if you will is to think
about going forward in this annual
meeting cycle with a warrant article
that would do perhaps somewhat what we
did with with dredging last year to say
let's proceed with
the effort to have Tom Pierre be the
first one that we do put out the dollar
amount in total it mentioned that we
intend to go to the state just as we did
with with dredging and if the state
grants us it could be up to two million
dollars then obviously the the demand
would decrease the other aspect and I
have not explored this as much and it's
impacted in part by the success at
Allen's project you may remember that
we've been sort of holding back from
looking to one other source which is the
Seaport bond council because we had kind
of two projects that weren't really
showing the kind of progress that they'd
like to see so how the Seaport bond
Council might enter into a further you
know discount if you will off the cost
to the town is something that we all we
all want to spend time and understand
and push forward so I think I'm going to
stop there just saying aye so what I
wanted what I believe we're picturing to
consider for the for this annual Town
Meeting year would be to go forward with
a request of the town to appropriate and
go forward with construction the
permitting page that you have the one
page that I showed you shows that that's
pretty doable and I pushed Eric pretty
hard today I said I want this to be a
reasonable calendar I don't want it to
be a wanna be you know a wish wish we'll
make it and he said look we're gonna
have to work hard especially with all
the other you know boards in the town
and Tom assured me that he would help
you know internally he said with that I
think this is this is doable so that
would be our thought and that we would
propose that in an article again as I
said done in sort of two two fashions
that grow the gross number something in
the order of four and a half million
dollars is when I'm recalling on a we
had cost that were they set in 2018 and
we
going forward into 2020 so you've got a
you know escalate them for inflation and
and then at the same time be be prepared
to file with the municipal vulnerability
program for a grant okay thank you Joe I
asked them all my questions this morning
so I'm good how about any questions you
already know the answers you have any
leading question hi Bill I'm just on
this chart it looks like the DEP there's
a chapter 91 minor modification yes is
that it it's it's actually a very
interesting point is that already in
process or let me let me explain I noted
that myself circled it and it is one of
the reasons why the timing if you were
to if you were to look at the other
schedules which were much rougher
because this is just we're not as far
along I asked him I said well why is it
that you think we can proceed with this
as a minor modification whereas the
other two would be a new and new
certificate
the answer is part partly sort of
legislative in the sense of what else
has happened to town Pier during the
period of a chapter 91 license Shepard
91 licenses go for a very long time
Ellen is it 20 years so to the extent
that we have been in front of the
agencies that grant chapter 91 licenses
and we've done stuff with compeer or
extending the the the wharfs that we put
in on an annual basis generally that's
done with special permits but deals and
Thomas had gone back done the homework
realized that they had a chance to
request and a not new but about a
modification of an existing chapter 91
and they have a close enough
relationship with the southeast regional
director that he said you know I think
this is a reason this is a reasonable
request that's so that's that that's why
the the difference between that and the
other two and if if can we apply for
both grant programs or does it
does the state sort of say hey choose
one either seaport bond or that's one of
the questions that I don't know the
answer to and it's one that we clearly
want to pursue and in part it's a
strategy question for the sheriff are we
are we far enough along with the suport
bond counsel that this is this is a
reasonable request or should we stay
within I mean this governor has really
made a point of this resiliency issue
and they they know it and and he's
talking about pushing you know more
money in that direction State does have
a six hundred and eighty million dollar
surplus this fiscal year just just
completed and he's talking about aiming
some some of those funds so I would just
say I appreciate that this has been a
really kind of methodical process and so
from time to time you've come in to say
hey you know here's our analysis about
how high we need to sort of build
everything - what do we think here's
it's it's very helpful particularly on a
big project like this to get those
periodic updates and I think when it
comes time to request something from
Town Meeting showing that we've had this
diligent public process is is going to
be really helpful I know there's been
some talk over time about you know do
you do them all at once so there may be
some cost synergies and things like that
by the same token and I appreciate your
being here for the financial piece in
some ways kind of pacing things out it
fits better financially but it also say
kind of for Town Meeting you know hey
this is this is this is phase one mm-hmm
and this is what's going to happen I
think the last thing I would say is just
you know we have a lot of different
capital needs and to me the resiliency
here is so important because you have
route 3a you have sewer pumping stations
I mean the the potential consequences of
flooding in that area are really
significant and so as it as it comes
time to
make the case to town meeting I think
that's going to be really important to
do because this is this to me is not a
nice to do this is a must do not that to
be to be clear not that doing these
three wharves alone solves all of our
problems because there are other
vulnerabilities but it is interesting I
think you're all aware that the multiple
vulnerability process that we went
through identified flooding as the
highest you know level risk that the
town faces so I think we're trying to
put our resources where where they're
needed long term and as we know it's
both sea level rise which is tides and
then you also have storm surge and
that's a difficult and something you
said earlier sort of for me again kind
of this staged approach is sometimes
when you do the first one you learn a
lot and so you know that it's kind of
resonating with me as far as how to you
know how to best best approach this
especially where the state is still
feeling their way on this this new grant
program you know they're not they Eric
told me today that they just hired four
more eea and I don't even know what eea
stands for but personnel to me to help
manage this grant request process so
they're they're learning they may do two
or three RFR as a year and we'll be in a
position to view be ready for those the
point that he did emphasize you know Joe
asked the question this morning do you
have to have all your permits before you
make your application and the answer was
the closer you are the better
it's called shovel-ready concept that
we're all very aware yeah I would say
especially if it's a new program and the
governor is putting a lot into it the
governor wants to be able to have some
success stories to a point to and they
you think about east school back in 2007
we said hey let's be like ready to go so
that when the MSBA starts we're a good
community were solid we've we've got all
our ducks in a row
it's kind of what we're doing here thank
you good question sure the audience
thanks for being here no Jim
Jim Watson 2001 welcome sweet well
that's an amazing presentation but we're
talking about raising the level of the
wolf's a couple feet but does that leave
the areas between them unprotected or
assistant wall so that was what I was
responding to Mary when I said even if
we do and it's not a couple of feet it's
three and a half feet so it's it's a
it's a significant increase from where
we are now and we and we got to that
after very careful thought about well
what are we trying to do how many years
are we trying to look out and you
remember the kleinfeld the report talked
about looking at 2030 and then 2070 in
which so somewhere you know beyond 2030
but not out fifty years because it's
just very hard to tell so that's that
one aspect but you're absolutely correct
you know to the extent for example when
when 3a is reconstructed we have the
rotary and the rotary is one of one of
the low spots and technically the wall
by the rotary is not the state's it's
ours it's the time so we may have during
that reconstruction to look at that one
more kind of opportunistic piece there
are things that can be done on a
short-term basis if you know a major
storm is coming
towns in in flood flow near flood prone
areas do have these temporary kind of
jersey barriers that can be put in place
and I could foresee this this might be
twenty years from now where the we would
we would set a line that would say okay
we're going to start at Iron Horse Pier
and we're going to close off route 3a to
ship Street with these temporary
barriers that would might be there for a
couple of days might be just one tide
cycle and other similar gaps in the
that'll be done between the worst to yes
so three and a half feet higher yes when
the president Whitney Wharf correct not
not with new or Whitney Wharf is already
at the height that we are then we are
targeting that's it's it's sixteen point
two feet above mean low
water today's tide was 12 feet it's when
we have storm surge that adds another
three or four that we get in trouble
I'll be around to see these Italian
thank you Jim
thank you Bill appreciate it in the
interest of our audience I'd like to I'd
like to move to number nine the Town
Hall Study Committee discussion I see
mr. Carey in the audience and I looks
like we lost mr. Carvin but appreciated
his attendance so you know for me I
think one of the themes of the evening
this evening is kind of getting back to
business right
we've we we've worked really hard over
the last several years on the lead-up to
the purchase of the water company and
Mary continues to pull the laboring oar
on behalf of the board in conjunction
with the water transaction but we have a
lot of business to do and I think
tonight is one of those meetings where
you see us really digging into the
business of the town and and it's sort
of on the heels of Mary's discussion
with respect to capital needs and
capital projects you might recall that
this board asked a group of citizens to
come together and think about the town
hall campus and a sort of a bigger
vision for the Town Hall campus and I
think there the reality of the lineup of
capital projects is that you know we've
got schools and fire stations and and
wharves and a lot of expenditures kind
of in our pipeline and one question I
think I had was with respect to this
building that serves so many people so
well and houses so many of our services
and employees might there be ways to
work within the current physical plant
to relieve some of the workplace issues
that we have and service related issues
that we have you know or maybe not but
are there sort of smaller capital
projects shorter term capital projects
that we might take on to address some of
those needs so so I I asked to put it on
the agenda because I thought it was
worth us
considering and you know I think my my
sense of the good work of the Town Hall
Study Committee was they they talked to
every single department they came up
with a fairly lengthy questionnaire
about usage and service levels that I
think would bring a great deal of
expertise to this kind of more directed
discussion and I think where I was kind
of going with this was in order to try
to maximize efficiency around the
knowledge base that this group or T has
would be to ask them to work with Tom
and Michele on a on a kind of a timeline
and a project basis directed through the
Board of Selectmen office you know that
potentially would give us some things to
think about in time for potentially this
town meeting cycle so that was the other
reason I think for the timing tonight is
if we're going to do that we need to get
to work pretty quickly and again to me
it made sense again given that given
that sort of compressed timeline to
bring together folks who have already
spent a great deal of time thinking
about this so that's where I am on it I
don't know whether you've had a chance
to think about it and have any pretty
thoughts you'd like to share
I've spoken to Tom about it as well and
I think this is absolutely the way to go
and now is the time to do it there are
needs and you know I've been down in the
Senior Center and that's which is part
of this and I'm really encouraged that
you're moving in this direction I don't
want the public to think that this is
the long-term Sol's oh yeah I think what
we're what we're talking about here are
some short-term things that will help us
live within the space we have but I
think the tricky part of this is going
to be what's that what's that Goldilocks
amount of improvements that that makes a
difference particularly I think in the
senior center where
and I think we're gonna hear a lot of
that tomorrow when we go there but I I
don't want people to kind of go oh okay
Senior Center Town Hall that's all done
because if you know again you look at
the rising senior population the space
that's there is not nearly adequate
enough and I think I'm all for making
improvements to it but let's make sure
we brand this the right way because this
is this isn't this isn't the solve and
we may you know in short order we may
find a long term opportunity may present
itself as we're continuing to go about
the business of the town so right that's
just no I completely agree and I think
that macness exercise is not unlike what
we've undertaken with respect to other
buildings and in particular the schools
right so sometimes we know we have a
longer term fix that needs to occur but
the timeline to get to that fix doesn't
doesn't provide I think the real need at
the moment so you know Jon Farriss from
time to time will say we need a capital
infusion to breathe a little more life
into a particular space and so Mary's
absolutely right I don't I am certainly
not by this suggestion proposing that
this is the fix for the Town Hall campus
because the reality is the reality is
that the functions here have outgrown
the space and that we're bumping up
against really our ability to provide
the kind of services we need to provide
in this building in in the way that we
want to provide it and that's not you
know this isn't also thinking that we
need to Taj Mahal but we do need you
know we do need a physical plant and a
parking arrangement that allows people
to come here and get the services they
need participate the programs they want
to participate in and for our employees
to have suitable safe work space and you
know it may be that the committee comes
back and there's not much we can do but
I feel like I guess I feel like we at
least on a
the question are there some short-term
dollars we could spend to to breathe a
little life for a couple more years as
we continue to think about other
alternatives because even if we had a
solution today right it was going to
take time right my understanding is that
the senior center has commissioned an
architect that has been or I'm
commissioned as a strong okay has has
gotten some recommendations from an
architect and someone who who deals with
senior spaces that that that will be
helpful additional input beyond the body
of work so again I just would let's
let's take all of the intelligence that
we have Tom do you want anything you'd
like to offer no okay sorry sorry
can you sorry
Tom Carrey
1131 mainstream and I chair the Town
Hall facilities Study Committee and and
I've got some long-term familiarity with
this building the there is no question
when when we started this project it was
a 1991 report that we had a whole bunch
of separate buildings single purpose
single use out of date
no handicapped accessibility and we were
looking at huge amounts of money going
into each one of them and everyone had
worn articles I want this for my
building I want that for the other
building at the same time we were
sitting with a 90 thousand square foot
vacant former central junior high that
had been shut down upon the failure of
an override for the school's hello we'd
had proposals to knock this building
down and sell off the house lights to
help repair these other inadequate
buildings so the planning really was
thinking started after that report and
it was 93 when the study when the the
vision of you could have a campus you
could have a Civic Center we could
consolidate a lot of places and get
efficiencies you've got meeting rooms
available for more than one organization
and so on and that's a long time ago it
was completed in 1998 if the so we're 25
years out really from completion or
certainly from the study interestingly
this project was the first major
a project for town infrastructure
capital infrastructure buildings not how
often you're replacing your automobiles
since 67 when the Town Hall and the
library had been built which in the Town
Hall by then except for one select one
no longer this was totally inadequate
you had the police we were inadequate
the Senior Center was in five hundred
square feet of space in her C house and
so the town bought the vision that we
should renovate this move all of those
separate places in here get those
efficiencies and dispose of the
properties the accountants building down
next to old derby used to be the school
building we sold it off it's on the tax
rolls
the dentist is where the on 3a is where
the police station used to be that's
productive and I think it's fair to say
not only was this project well received
at the time but in retrospect it has
been an enormous success the Senior
Center at least in my discussions with
various seniors and the people over
there the general consensus is boy if we
could stay here we'd love it but we
don't have enough space they went from
from three and three hundred square feet
to five thousand square feet our Senior
Center was the talk of the South Shore
other communities were coming to look at
this place and to look at this beautiful
Senior Center in the process of our work
in the committee I've personally visited
situate Marshfield Hanover Rockland
Wellesley we are no longer the talk of
the South Shore situate had something
like
nine or twelve thousand one and was
adding another four Marshfield was was
up high M was adding another nine so in
terms of what other communities have for
the seniors who are in the general
population we've fallen way behind so
the need for the Senior Center I think
it's clear in our studies we have been
looking at options to keep it in this
building because it's the right spot in
terms of access to police access to the
treasurer access to assistance from town
and the law the police station had gone
from the small building on three eight
to ten thousand square feet and there
was swimming in space and compared to
what they had been in before that's no
longer the case and as time passes there
are other needs the same can be said
pretty much for most apartments all
through the building in one degree or
another but it is clear to me that there
are things personally speaking that can
be done to dramatically improve the
working situation here at town law which
has really been intolerable for quite
some time
zoning restrictions on use of parts of
the building which have been in
existence from the beginning because of
perceived inadequacy of parking parking
is strangling the ability of the school
department to bring its people in to
meet it's strangling the senior centered
strangling everything so some of these
issues can be addressed some
modifications within the building can be
done there are some other options I
think if
we continue to study the original
concept of a campus here in the midst of
20 acres of publicly owned land in the
center of the community with the
synergies of joint uses that it entails
we will be looking toward a future that
will be just as well received as the
last quarter century has been as part of
the overall picture that you're
describing with this hundred million
dollars or so of projects my position
would be that some of the needs that are
being met in adequately here at Town
Hall are just as deserving and need to
be done as some of the others so I know
I've looked at the numbers it's a choice
that town is going to have to make but
unfortunately the ones that are being
dealt with here haven't had anything
done in a structural capacity growth for
the last 25 years so we've got this
pattern of you build a couple of new
buildings for town operations and then a
quarter century goes by before you say
oops we have to do something else again
our tax base isn't going to look too
good if credit rating agencies start
asking themselves why a community like
that is providing fire safety services
out of 80 year old buildings is why I
think heaping their infrastructure the
people who've paid the taxes while their
kids were in school and our thinking
isn't this a wonderful community to
remain in are gonna have second thought
if the only seniors who are getting the
kind of services that
again are those who can afford several
hundred thousand dollars as a deposit
and go in to a private lifestyle so we
all know that the money that's spent if
it's spent well on town services is
critical to the entire community I don't
like the idea that we have let another
quarter of a century oh by without
putting aside a depreciation fund for
the day when the increase in needs had
to be met it's sort of like our unmet
needs for pensions on the whole we need
to I think pay more attention to that
rather than just building them when we
need them you know the schools worn out
so we build a new school and then one of
these days the fire department is in
line or the police are in line or the
seniors are in line so I applaud the
extent to which you're looking at these
long term financial needs and the
numbers and I recognize that that has to
all be taken into account and it will be
in the community we'll be making some
choices on these large structural
projects but I think it is worth taking
a hard look at how much we can
accomplish to improve the lives of
everyone in this building police senior
everyone town staff meeting rooms
availability just being able to get in
the place to be able to use it clearly
other communities have done it there are
ways to try to address it to ameliorate
some of these problems and I would
certainly echo the notion that this is
not in any way a desire to throw
all of these various departments under
the bus or put them aside as we're we're
forgoing long term study I take your
charge to be continued with the long
term study and analysis and options and
to add a more targeted shorter term
perception of what can we do in the mean
time to make things better around here
and I'm happy to work with Tom and
Michelle and I'm sure that we can come
up with at least something to because
there's plenty that needs amelioration
Thanks thank you so so if you if you're
amenable then maybe for next time I I
could work with Tom her show on kind of
a mini charge yeah I mean I would I
would love On January 20th right to have
Warren article and and I think I think
one way or another I think there's gonna
be a school on the Town Meeting warrant
for April I just I have that feeling and
I I want to be able to you know I think
whatever we're asking the town for when
there's a big ask I think different
parts of the community want to look and
go okay somewhere in this warrant
there's a little something for me yeah
really I really want something and and
and and I I do understand that there are
a lot of different needs in this group
I'm particularly interested in the
Senior Center because I think for many
of these folks the ask the ask on a
school project MSBA or no MSBA is is
going to be a big one and for some the
third in ten years and so I I want this
coming Town Meeting you don't want it to
be divisive so I think that that short
term piece is gonna be super duper
important
okay so so Tom just so you're clear
I think I'll work with Tom and Michelle
to draft some language and I think our
intent would be to have it on the agenda
to vote next Tuesday right okay all
right thank you thank you appreciate it
okay and then the next moving back to
number eight which is the naming bylaw
discussion so you know this this the the
reason why I think I wanted to have it
on the agenda for us to talk about
tonight is is I think the importance and
we've seen the importance of public
private partnerships with respect to
municipal projects and given again the
capital projects that are on the horizon
there are components of certain of those
projects that lend themselves I think to
to private support you know in
particular as as folks know the Maritime
Center has been fundraising you know
over the last several years and will
continue to do that to meet their
obligations with respect to the wharf
area you know
South Shore Country Club has the Friends
of South Shore Country Club there are
folks in this town who above and beyond
their tax contributions contributed
philanthropically to important municipal
projects and so you know one of the
questions is do our bylaws kind of keep
pace with best practices in
public-private partnerships and in
particular in recognizing and
celebrating those people who step up
above and beyond what they're required
to do and you know and and contribute
philanthropically in a way that
alleviates the tax burden or augments
important municipal projects and so I
think and I did have the opportunity to
talk to Ed zigfried who was on the
original naming bylaw committee several
years ago and
and did confirm with him that at that
time that we didn't consider codifying
rules with respect to public-private
partnerships so the bylaw you know
speaks to naming public buildings and
public lands but it doesn't contemplate
those situations where there could be
significant private dollars that are
utilized in either constructing or again
augmenting public buildings or public
lands and you know we have seen in
particular that the generosity of the of
the people of this town in the fields
project at the high school you know it's
a beautiful facility it's a beautiful
community facility and it wouldn't be
wouldn't have been possible without
significant private support so I guess I
just I think this is the wave of our
future I think that so so I guess I
don't want the town to have any
impediments artificial impediments to
facilitating really fulsome private
philanthropic support for municipal
projects and so my suggestion would be
that we get you know we get a small
group together again I would think a
very targeted a targeted ask on this to
take a look at what peer communities are
doing take a look at the importance of
of private support in this town and you
know potentially suggest amendment
language by January 20th to this bylaw
so I don't know whether I've had a
chance to think about that and have any
comments on that and I've read I've read
the article article 40 and there are
clear limitations here and we've got
away the need for funding against
what those who have come before us has
viewed as appropriate for how the town
should be naming buildings lands
institutions so I think having a
committee that looked at it and looked
at how our pure communities have
addressed it is appropriate next oh yeah
I mean I think we've heard over the last
couple years
I know I've heard from people who have
felt like their aspects there are there
are aspects of this that don't
contemplate private dollars and
therefore it's I think sometimes people
are having a difficult time navigating
through I would you know I think with
something like this because this this
arose from a very emotional issue in the
town so I want us to handle it in a in a
way that is really constructive so you
know I I know it's October 29th but I
think we should in some way try to
advertise to make people aware that if
they want to help out and serve on this
and I'm not suggesting we spend like
eight weeks
drumming things up but to me it's going
to be important that people feel like
they had the opportunity to put their
name forward for consideration it
doesn't rule out reaching out to people
if we think it's okay but I just think
that the town meeting is going to look
at the process by which any refinements
were done as much as the refinements
themselves so I think we want to handle
it you know handle it in that way and it
would it would strike me that in
particular there's you know in terms of
the procedure there's a role here that
the historic Commission plays and so it
would again I I'm thinking about who
would be stakeholders that would be we
want citizens on this committee but I
think we want to make sure certain
voices are at the table and so that you
know that those pieces I think are
important
you know we've got so I don't remember
for meeting on the 12th at you know
normally when we do a committee like
this we we we sort of publicize it for
like two weeks and make a point on sort
so you know what we I'm thinking you
know Carol is here from the anchor we
can get something in the journal we can
put out Hingham notice I just want to do
a blast to make people aware it's on a
radar screen so that people have a
chance I agree with you I think a small
group is better given the time frame I
guess the question I have is you know I
think there were a number of citizens
including mr. Siegfried and others who
put a lot of time and thought into this
and I think it would be important to me
that that a group that is looking at
this really kind of start by getting a
good download from that committee
because right I think that they did they
did important thoughtful sensitive work
in a period of time and I don't want to
lose that right I think that's a great
point so so what is it the 19th 19th
yeah so if we if we could do the blast
almost starting tomorrow right and and
then plan to have something on the
agenda for the 19 are you thinking 5
people 3 always do odd numbers yeah so
well I would say no more than 5 ok yeah
I think that would be my real yeah 5 may
be the right number I mean I I I hear
your point that you know I don't want to
short change the process piece of this
you know initially I would have thought
3 but I think that you know again
depending on what the response is maybe
to the to the ask from people that would
inform maybe the size but I would my
view would be no more than 5 I think
it's a pretty compressed time period so
you just pragmatically write you need
you need a focus to be able to get
together
I would also say that there's probably
gonna be an aspect of this that involves
council and so it'll be important for
you guys you know to know when to engage
council at the right time so that if a
group is heading in a direction that
legally doesn't work we're not you know
we're not spinning our wheels I would
just also suggest with with these groups
Tom and Michelle I know you're you've
got and caring you've got periodic
updates with addcom I think this is a
time of year when addcom would find it
helpful to know this because they're
gonna want to have liaisons and have
people start attending the town hall
study committee meetings and really kind
of getting embedded in this work so I
meet with that gon weekly yeah on
leadership I'll I'll bring them up to
speed on this one thing I was wondering
is could we on the fifth maybe come back
and discuss a final charge on the 19th
right okay and and Carol I think for you
know purposes of the anchor this is this
is looking at the existing vial I mean I
think without a charge we sort of know
what we want to do here yeah so I think
we can start getting the word out it's
really yeah so I would say to Mary's
point it's looking at the existing bylaw
and reviewing pure communities and
making recommendations with respect to a
potential amendment of the existing
bylaw to take account of public-private
partnerships so municipal buildings and
lands that would be funded or augmented
by private dollars
so anyway I think again it did sort of
trying to move us in the right direction
and anticipate I think continued private
support for the many municipal projects
that we have we're more grateful for
that any questions from the public on
the naming
okay so charge on the on the fifth
you'll get the word out or Talent Bank
applications and we'll look to hopefully
make some appointments on the 19th
Alibag yeah yeah sorry they're
unavailable online yes and they can be
submitted to my office thanks Carol do
we have any appointments tonight
I've got the list here but I don't see
the names I would make a motion to
appoint Daniel Miller Dempsey to the
traffic and Safety Committee to fill an
unexpired term ending June 30th 2021
second all those in favor aye
it's like to thank mr. Dempsey he
actually went to the traffic committee
meeting to do something he was there to
opine on an issue loved what they did
his son was there said I want to be part
of this law and it's just great that
when people engage in their government
and want to step up
so as Glenn's sparkling personality and
I move that we appoint is it Matt Matt
Matthew person that Matthew person to
the traffic and Safety Committee for a
three year term ending June 30 20 22
second any further discussion all those
in favor aye all right and nothing
against Glenn but I believe sergeant
kill Hawaii has been attending okay and
I think we get some one-day liquor
licenses she was not here but I'm
assuming Michelle everything's in order
yes he's reviewed them and doesn't have
any issues with those or the the
sidewalk requests as well so I have
legal seafood I've got East Elementary
do we have the woman's
I have one if you need it
yeah ice is one page oh there we go okay
so we got the end areas Main Street yep
okay oh I see yeah okay so I would
accept a motion to approve the
application of legal seafoods LLC do d
be a legal c96 Derby Street for a change
of officer to the LLC board of managers
from Edward Pentagon pentaghast to Eric
Chris as outlined in the letter from the
Massachusetts alcoholic beverages
Control Commission dated September 20
2019 so moved second all those in favor
all right
I would accept a motion to approve the
issuance of a special one-day wine and
malt beverages license to Suzanne
garland on behalf the East Elementary
School PTO for the East elementary
parents social to be held at the hang of
community center on Friday November 15
2019 from 7 p.m. to 10:00 p.m. so moved
second all those in favor all right I
would accept a motion to approve the
issuance of a special one-day all
alcoholic beverages license to Molly
Roberts on behalf of the Hingham Woman's
Club for evergreen evening to be held at
the Hingham Heritage Museum on Saturday
December 7 2019 from 7:00 p.m. to 11:00
p.m. so moved second all in favor hi
and I would accept a motion to approve
the request of the Hingham downtown
Association to close Main Street between
Elm and north streets and south street
between central and wor streets and to
use the sidewalks and tile cap for
Christmas in the square on Friday
December 6 2019 from 5:00 p.m. to 9:00
p.m. so moved second all in favor all
right
can't really vote against Christmas I
know come on
rights reports nothing on my end thank
you you said you did fine
so just so I'm not sure if everyone
understands this but whenever we have
these large storms whether they're
blood-related storms are more closed off
in winter storms that that the town
incurred significant cost of often FEMA
will declare disaster zones nationally
and then you end up with a scenario
where when you tap when you track your
expenses locally appropriate ly you can
receive reimbursements for those
expenses through the federal government
and because of the efforts of both chief
Olson and chief Murphy as well as
Superintendent Sylvester we've recently
received FEMA reimbursements to the tune
of ninety two thousand eight hundred
dollars for debris cleanup
19900 olives for boat ramp repairs and
bathing beach parking lot repairs and
thirteen thousand $260 for damage to the
schools so again what I was talking
about is trying to find money outside of
the Hingham tax base to offset our
operations and and this is the kind of
effort that happens on a regular basis
so Joe a couple issues topics the first
is compressor station I've received
communications I think other members of
the board have received it town
officials have received it so I want to
do two things first give an update on
where the litigation stands and then
also talk about some notices last week
on October 22nd the town of Hingham
joined with the town of Weymouth and the
cities of Braintree and Quincy then
seeking review of the decision of the
mass Department of Environmental
Protection to issue a permit for the
proposed compression compressor station
in Weymouth on Ruth
a the petition was filed in the United
States Court of Appeals for the First
Circuit under the federal natural gas
act which gives the US Court of Appeals
original and exclusive jurisdiction to
review the DEP s decision the petition
mainly concerns emissions from the
proposed compressor station of nitrogen
oxides and formaldehyde there were three
issues raised I don't want to go into
them in week that excruciating depth the
first issue was whether or not a motor
an electric motor should have been
considered as an option the second issue
concerned selective catalytic reduction
whether or not that should have been
added to the turbine in order to reduce
any wax emissions
that's nitric oxide emissions and the
third issue concerns levels of
formaldehyde those are the three issues
that have been appealed to the First
Circuit the schedule is that the DEP is
expected to be filing their briefs in
December 11th then Algonquin files their
opening brief on December 18th reply
briefs are filed in January no hearing
date has been set although this is on an
expedited expedited scheduling basis
with the court and it looks as if the
court will be acting sometime in the
spring although that date is certainly
not set in stone so we'll certainly keep
the public updated as we get information
second we've I've heard communications
and questions from members of the public
about discharges from the existing
facility just to be clear those
discharges are from the existing
facilities for the not subject to the
proposed permits for the proposed
facility so I think people were thinking
that limitations that might have applied
in what's being proposed applied to the
existing they do not second has been my
understanding that Algonquin has been
providing notice to the abutting
communities
Hingham is not an abutting community
with respect to where the discharges
have been taking place although I
believe you can contact Algonquin on
their website to request that you be
notified so that's that's my update
there with respect to the compressor
station second there is a meeting
scheduled tomorrow October 30th Council
on Aging it is an open house members of
the public are invited to attend members
of the Board of Selectmen will be
attending and it's really going to be
our chance to communicate with those
people who are using the Senior Center
about their needs and for them to learn
about the town what's going on in the
town so I would encourage members of the
public who are interested to attend next
mary and i attended and karen one and
two but did not could not attend Phyllis
Chapman's one hundred and second
birthday celebration today it was
incredible it was uplifting and we are
all looking forward to celebrating her
hundred and third birthday next year
Phyllis is a sweetheart
so there was a sweetheart tree and very
nice fantastic it was and it was very
well attended and then I don't know if
anyone else is gonna cover the that
master plan schedule for when they're
gonna be having their meetings we've
somebody I was gonna but good I'm out of
also the master plan committee is going
to be having visit visioning events and
members of the public are encouraged to
attend they are Monday November 18th
from 10:00 a.m. to noon Wednesday
November 20th from 7 p.m. to 9 p.m. and
Saturday November 23rd from 11:30 a.m.
to 2:00 p.m. all
those are on the second floor of town
hall and the same material will be
covered at each of those events so you
really need only attend one of those
they're they're really meant to be small
discussion groups so you'd be able to
come and share your thoughts about what
you like about town in town what you not
so I would like to obtain SJM so you
know like we talked about tonight we're
all in this together and you know the
master planning group is working really
hard to to undertake these outreach
efforts so we really encourage you to to
attend and then with respect to the
November 18th session that's from 10:00
a.m. to 12:00 I do want to say that
there is babysitting available for a
small fee here at Town Hall nary a
couple of things I just just to build on
what Joe mentioned about Phyllis Chapman
it gets back to the Senior Center and
you know Karen you know this but Phyllis
is part of an exercise group at the
Senior Center and this is a group of
about 40 or 50 women and this is you
know this is about it's about wellness
it's about community it's about
friendship and this is a group that
takes care of one another and there as
someone said to me today we are each
other's family and when I think of a
Senior Center that's really what it's
all about it's about building community
and a place where just a place to
cultivate that and it it reinforced to
me just the the real mission of the
Senior Center in so many different ways
is is nurturing you know the minds the
hearts and the bodies of of such a big
part of our population I'm getting to
the younger scale I do just want to
mention that every Hingham high school
sports team from the fall are making the
playoffs this year and you know girls
soccer got a tie last night and they're
you know they're an edge just all the
teams are in and so our
congratulations and and lastly just a
kind of a quick water update because I
think sometimes there's a lot of things
that are going on but but we get
questions so just so people know you
know we are still in the good husbandry
period where Aquarion is operating the
water system we envision that as tom
went through this a few weeks ago at one
of our meetings this the schedule calls
for the town
assuming ownership no earlier than March
first and that's just because this is a
complex transaction
eversource Aquarian town of Hingham
we're all working cooperatively but we
all want to make sure that we do our due
diligence the request for a proposal for
a water system operator is out Tom and
Michelle were part of the site visit
that took place a few weeks ago so that
continues to move along and also you
know when when the financial model was
put together and all the while we've
we've been talking about this the town
has always consistently said that if if
town meeting voted to authorize this
we're going to bring in some expertise
to help us with this transition this
transition is not something that we can
do alone so again in a in a public
process the town has hired environmental
partners group to provide technical
expertise mr. Jeffery nodding a
forty-year Town Administrator who is
helping with a lot of the municipal
aspects of all the necessary
requirements it's a it's a business plan
with the Department of Environmental
Protection it's the creation of rules
and regulations the town also continues
to benefit from the guidance of mr.
Robert College former DEP Commissioner
so you know what what we're really doing
here is bringing the necessary technical
and specialist resources to bear to make
sure that this transition is smooth for
all concerned the transition and
evaluation committee is meeting every
couple weeks they just met last night
all of their meetings are being taped
they're being broadcast these are public
meetings they are being posted in
Holland Cohasset
as we continue to move along there is
there's a there are a lot of different
parts of this that are going and again
the the DEP and and the word that we
continue to get from them is they they
feel like this is moving in an
appropriate direction at an appropriate
pace so you know as in the weeks to come
there will be more updates with respect
to the RFP again the TNA committee is is
meeting to review things and it just
continues to move along okay I have one
follow-up hearing the discussion about
Phyllis Chapman and the group of women
who are exercising I didn't realize it
was only women so if there are guys out
there who are not exercising get over
there okay and on that note I will
convene I'd like to convene an executive
session for review approval and
potential release a prior executive
session minutes pursuant to
Massachusetts general law after 30 a
section 22 and 21 a 7 the board will not
return to open session this requires a
roll roll call vote Mary all right
you